CHAPTER 2.1
Installing Python 3.7 on a Cloud Playground

Learn how to install Python 3 using pyenv (https://github.com/pyenv/pyenv) on a CentOS 7 that has code-server pre-installed to provide a full development environment.

Note: This course uses Python 3.7 and you will definitely run into issues if you are using Python < 3.7.

Picking the Right Cloud Playground Image
If you plan on following along with the course on your local workstation, you'll want to make sure you have a good development environment set up. But, if you want to follow along exactly with the course, then you'll want to create a Cloud Playground server (use 2 or 3 units) using the "CentOS 7 w/ code-server" image. This image will give us a server with code-server (https://github.com/cdr/code-server) pre-installed (VS Code running on the server and accessible through the browser).

Using code-server to Program on the Server
By using the public IP address (or domain name) of the server and its port 8080, we can access code-server from our browser which has a full development environment with a terminal available to us. We'll be redirected to the page being served over HTTPS and, depending on our browser, we'll need to click a few buttons to acknowledge that we know the certificate is self-signed.

Installing pyenv
Installing Python from source can be a great learning experience, but it is a little tedious. For this course, we're going to instead install pyenv (https://github.com/pyenv/pyenv) which will allow us to install and switch between multiple different Python versions more easily.

To get started, we need to make sure we have some development dependencies installed so we can pull down the pyenv repository. We're using the --skip-broken flag because the "CentOS 7 w/ code-server" playground image already has Git installed. If you're using a different image, you can install Git using the package manager for that system.

sudo yum install -y --skip-broken git gcc zlib-devel bzip2-devel readline-devel sqlite-devel


Now we need to clone the pyenv (https://github.com/pyenv/pyenv) repository.

$ git clone https://github.com/pyenv/pyenv.git ~/.pyenv


For pyenv to be useful, we'll need to set a few environment variables and run a command when our shell is loading. We'll add those to our ~/.bashrc file so this action happens as soon as our shell is initialized.


$ echo 'export PYENV_ROOT="$HOME/.pyenv"' >> ~/.bashrc
$ echo 'export PATH="$PYENV_ROOT/bin:$PATH"' >> ~/.bashrc
$ echo -e 'if command -v pyenv 1>/dev/null 2>&1; then\n  eval "$(pyenv init -)"\nfi' >> ~/.bashrc


Before we can use pyenv, we'll need to reload our shell:

$ exec $SHELL


Finally, let's install Python 3.7.6

$ pyenv install 3.7.6


Now we can check and switch between versions of Python using pyenv. To see the versions available to us, we'll use the pyenv versions command:

$ pyenv versions
* system (set by /home/cloud_user/.pyenv/version)
  3.7.6


To change our active version, we'll use pyenv shell <VERSION>:

$ pyenv shell 3.7.6
$ python --version
Python 3.7.6


We also have an executable for python3 and python3.7 that we can use. To make it apparent what version is being used throughout the course, you'll see that the commands use the python3.7 executable.


Upgrade Pip

The version of pip that we have might be up-to-date, but it's a good practice to try to update it after the installation. Let's update that now:

$ pip3.7 install --upgrade pip
Collecting pip
  Downloading https://files.pythonhosted.org/packages/57/36/67f809c135c17ec9b8276466cc57f35b98c240f55c780689ea29fa32f512/pip-20.0.1-py2.py3-none-any.whl (1.5MB)
     |????????????????????????????????| 1.5MB 3.1MB/s
Installing collected packages: pip
  Found existing installation: pip 19.2.3
    Uninstalling pip-19.2.3:
      Successfully uninstalled pip-19.2.3
Successfully installed pip-20.0.1


If you chose to install the Python extension, be sure to press the blue button to reload. Click Install at the bottom right-hand corner to install Pylint. Pylint is a source-code, bug, and quality checker for the Python programming language.